Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, ערב חג שמח, Erev Chag Sameach, and
חג שמח. Chag Sameach. We pick up, today's דף Daf is דף
פ, Daf Pe, 80. We're actually all on schedule, and with a
short דף Daf in front of us because there are very big
תוספות, Tosafots, ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem. סנהדרין Sanhedrin is a מסכת Masechet
where, I mean, it's not as bad as ברכות, Brachos, but you
know, סנהדרין Sanhedrin is a מסכת Masechet where you long for big
תוספות. Tosafots. All right, right, ברוך השם Baruch Hashem for big תוספות.
Tosafots. Yeah, okay, anyway, so we pick up at the bottom of
עין ט עמוד ב. Ayin Tes Amud Beis. And basically, the משנה
Mishna said if a murderer gets mixed up with other, with others,
they all get off scot-free, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you
throw them all in jail, putting them into a כיפה. Kippa. We'll
get later to discuss what כיפה Kippa is, but the פשט Pshat
of כיפה Kippa said it's basically just jail. So, you know, the
idea they get off scot-free makes sense,
but you throw them all in jail, well what did the innocent
people do? So you have to explain who are these other people
that the murderer got mixed up with. So the first explanation was
that these other people were convicted murderers, or convicted people of חייבי
מיתות, Chayvei Misas, doesn't matter whatever.
And then what you really have a problem, so but the guy
that got mixed up was somebody in which you actually
you know he was a murderer, they were about to pass judgment,
the court had deliberated, but they didn't technically pass judgment. So therefore
you can't actually execute him. So therefore the חכמים Chachamim say well
they all go scot-free, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says look, we
have nine convicted murderers, one that we know is a murderer, I'm
not setting them all scot-free, I'm just throwing them all in prison,
which makes an enormous amount of sense. Okay, it's interesting because you
could have said it was a little bit different. You could have
said they were nine people that were נגמר דינו Nigmar Dino and
one convicted murderer, but maybe that's a harder to imagine a scenario.
Anyway, that's one explanation, that was the first explanation, that was I
think רבא, Rava, who was it, no, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in
the name of שמואל. Shmuel.
Then, the גמרא Gemara gave the position of what do you call
it,
of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said no
no no, with people we would never do this, we would set
them all scot-free, like everybody would agree. I don't know why that's
so obvious, like you know, you got nine convicted murderers and one
guy you know is a murderer, why not just throw them all
in jail? So what? Really, so why not? Why can't you? I
don't know, I don't know what to tell you, I don't know.
Okay, he says but you would send them all, oh, and by
the way, the reason you can't convict the unconvicted guy is because
אין גומרים דינו אלא בפני בעל דין. Ein Gomerim Dino Ela Bifnei
Ba'al Din. So, which is not enough that he's somewhere in the
courtroom, you have to basically be able to look at him and
say you פלוני חייב. Ploni Chayav. So it doesn't matter, you would
bring the whole ten of them in, you could not finish, you
cannot do גמר דין. Gmar Din. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says for
whatever reason if it was people, we would have to, we don't
want to lock up the guy who's the non-convicted murderer even though
we know he's a murderer, and we would let them all go
scot-free, I really don't understand that but fine. And here we're talking
about the parallel case by an ox, okay. You have nine
שור הנסקל, Shor Niskals, what? Why would you call that a רוצח?
Rotzeach? It sounds like... I know, it's a very hard read of
the משנה, Mishna, there's no question. When do we ever call a
שור הנסקל Shor Niskal a רוצח? Rotzeach? It is a bizarre read
of the משנה, Mishna, okay, absolutely. Okay, so he says that's the
case, we have nine ox that are שור הנסקל, Shor Niskal, and
one that is killed somebody, it's a רוצח, Rotzeach, which as Michael's
absolutely correct, we never call that, it gets mixed up. And so
you can't, and so and that's the question. So the חכמים Chachamim
say well you can't do the גמר דין Gmar Din on the
ox, in the same way you couldn't do a גמר דין Gmar
Din on a person, כמיתת הבעלים כך מיתת השור. Kemisas Hab'alim Kach
Misas Hashor. So what do you do? You let them all, all
the oxen scot-free, which is very bizarre because if you just think
about it, the other ox are actually already שור הנסקל Shor Niskal
and you're letting them scot-free, nobody, well forget, they can go kill
somebody, and then who's going to benefit from them? They're אסור בהנאה
Assur B'hana'ah already. So what do you do? You just let them
out to graze for pasture for the rest of their lives? It's
very bizarre, they're oxen, just kill them all, stone them all, why
not? It's very strange. Then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you put
them all in כיפה, Kippa, which basically means you lock them all
up and you let them die, a Rifka עליו השלום Alav Hashalom
were here, you know she always raises that when you lock up
an animal and you let it die, right, so it's like she
was very upset about the whole צער בעלי חיים, Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim,
and she's completely right. And it doesn't explain it again, why not
just stone them all, like you had to stone nine of them,
just stone ten of them. So actually תוספות, Tosafot, I should say
one of these big תוספות Tosafots has a possibility that the גרסא
Girsa here is that the שור הנסקל Shor Niskal got mixed up
with nine innocent oxen. Then it makes sense why you could say
maybe let them free or רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say you're
not going to stone them but maybe we'll just lock them up.
Okay, anyway, so that's ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish explanation, but of course
it's a bizarre read of the word רוצח. Rotzeach. Okay, so now
we pick up at the last line, two words at the bottom
of עין ט עמוד ב, Ayin Tes Amud Beis, אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, let's get into this, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava,
אי הכי, i hachi, whether you read it like ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish or שמואל, Shmuel, who was it, רב אבא אמר שמואל, Rav
Abba Amar Shmuel, היינו דקתני, hi'nu de'katni, do either of those reads
make sense with... It's the ברייתא Braisa that we taught on this,
which is the ברייתא Braisa explains the משנה Mishnah says, אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, אפילו אבא חלפתא ביניהם. Afilu Abba Chalafta beineihem.
This would be true even if this great צדיק Tzaddik אבא חלפתא
Abba Chalafta was one of the people this murderer was mixed up
with. So first of all, that obviously says we're not reading it
like, like, what do you call it? Like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
An ox getting mixed up with אבא חלפתא Abba Chalafta doesn't make
sense. But besides that we're talking about people, it's like since the
חכמים Chachamim say you let them all free, right? So what does
it mean even if there was a צדיק Tzaddik among them? Of
course if there was a צדיק Tzaddik among them you would let
them all free. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says you put
them all in jail, how would you put them in jail if
אבא חלפתא Abba Chalafta was there? Like what sense does any of
this making? So clearly there is something missing from your explanation of
the משנה Mishnah because this line doesn't work with any of the
reads, just wait a minute. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so
רבא Rava says, הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. Here's how you have to
read the beginning of the משנה. Mishnah. We've all misunderstood the beginning
of the משנה. Mishnah. Here's the beginning of the משנה: Mishnah: שניים
שהיו עומדים ויצא חץ
מביניהם. Shnayim she-hayu omdim v'yatza chetz mibeineihem. That means, not misunderstood, it's
just he's completely adding a line in the משנה, Mishnah, he's changing
the משנה. Mishnah. But anyway, two people were standing, I mean again
this is so horrific considering the events just of recently of Las
Vegas, you know, two people are standing and one of them is
a shooter, and one of them shoots somebody, okay, and you don't
know which of the two it is. But one of those two
was אבא חלפתא, Abba Chalafta, okay, one of those two was the
biggest צדיק Tzaddik in the
world, okay. ויצא חץ מביניהם, V'yatza chetz mibeineihem, an arrow came from
one of those two, והרג, ve'harag, and it killed, שניהם פטורים, shneihem
peturim, they're both exempt because you don't know which one did it,
okay, you can't convict either. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve'amar Rabbi Yosei, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosei says, אפילו אבא חלפתא ביניהם, afilu Abba Chalafta beineihem,
even if אבא חלפתא Abba Chalafta was one of them you can't
say ah obviously it wasn't אבא חלפתא, Abba Chalafta, it was this
other guy. Doesn't matter. One guy is the world's biggest low-life, the
other guy is the world's biggest צדיק, Tzaddik, if you didn't see
who shot then they both get off. Of course the whole thing
is bizarre anyway because don't you need עדים edim and don't they
need התראה hatra'ah and don't they whatever? So you'd have to come
up with some scenario that they said it and whatever, like they
didn't see who they were talking to but I don't know, the
whole thing is bizarre and it's not and it's a very bizarre
read of the משנה Mishnah to adding a whole line to the
משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so that's the first thing it does is it
adds that line to the משנה. Mishnah. ונתערב באחרים, U'nesarev b'acherim, meaning
he was standing with somebody else. So this read is that a
רוצח שנתערב באחרים rotzeach shenisarev b'acherim means not we knew somebody was
a murderer and got mixed up, but we don't know who the
murderer is because there's a mix up of people. Right, exactly, right.
Okay, that now, ורבי יהודה אומר, v'Rabbi Yehuda omer, now, I'm sorry,
now בשור bishor and now let's go back to ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, why not? Because it makes it more bizarre to throw in
these oxen, but maybe now that we got the word רוצח rotzeach
addressing Michael's problem to mean something else, רוצח rotzeach does mean a
person. But רוצח שנתערב rotzeach shenisarev means is we don't know who
the murderer was to begin with because it was mixed up the
people, so that works with the word רוצח rotzeach as well, and
then we insert a new case that's not in the משנה Mishnah
at all. Oh, ופוטר רבי יהודה u'poter Rabbi Yehuda though? Well, we're
going to get to that, calm down. Okay, because we're first inserting
a case. So the first line refers to just the case of
כולם פטורים kulam peturim and everybody agrees to that. That's when we
don't know who the murderer is to begin with, okay, we don't
know who shot the arrow. And that's the word רוצח. rotzeach. Now
stick in the following line: והשור שנגמר דינו שנתערב בשוורים אחרים מעולים.
vehashor shenigmar dino shenisarev b'shvarim acherim me'ulim. Now here it actually says
what תוספות Tosfos was the question about the גרסא girsa before, okay,
but this is I think a better read for the reasons we
said: a שור shor that was a שור הנסקל shor haniskal that
got mixed, so it was נגמר דינו, nigmar dino, it was a
שור הנסקל shor haniskal and it got mixed up with nine other
oxen that were completely innocent oxen. Okay, so what do you do?
So the first position is rather than the פטורין peturin which had
been the position, the first position here יסקלו כולם, yisaklu kulam, it
doesn't matter, they're, you know, we're just going to stone them all
because they're oxen, you know, so whatever. And now the question is
why is that fair to the owners? So תוספות Tosfos says well,
you know, the owners of the other nine, so תוספות Tosfos says
well if one ox gets mixed up with nine others, what would
be the הלכה? halacha? First, you know, in terms of like ביטול
bittul of a mixture. So you would think you would say well
it's בטל ברוב, batel berov, right? The actual הלכה halacha is that
it is not. There's a whole discussion in זבחים Zevachim which is
what one minute which is what sort of which is what one
of these long תוספות Tosfos is about which is is that בעלי
חיים ba'alei chayim are חשיבי, chashivi, are important, and therefore they don't
lose their identity. Part of the way ביטול bittul works is, you
know, it's like it's like the thing sort of stops having its
own like like well, first of all, certainly a case of like
a ביטול bittul of לח בלח. lach belach. You know, you put
a small amount of something into a solution and it's like if
it's a trace element, it's like it's not there, as long as
it's like not cyanide or something. Okay. But anyway, so small, you
know, whatever, and that's like allergens, I'm serious, you know, that's why
for some things trace elements matter. But for the most part, if
it's a tiny trace thing, it lose completely loses identity. Case of
like יבש ביבש, yavesh beyavesh, solid objects, it's harder to say it
loses its identity because each thing is distinct. But nevertheless, and there's
a whole debate, how do you understand or something, right? But anyway,
it's a small, you know, whatever, and that's like allergens, I'm serious,
you know, that's why for some things trace elements matter, but for
the most part, if it's a tiny trace thing, it completely loses
identity. Case of like יבש ביבש, yavesh biyavesh, solid objects, it's harder
to say it loses its identity because each thing is distinct. But
and there's a whole debate, how do you understand ביטול bittul by
solid objects? But nevertheless, a major approach is that solid objects works
the same as like a type of a solution, and if you
have like, you know, sixty apples here, if none of them are
particularly significant, like, you know, whatever, sixty potatoes, so you look at
it as a pile of potatoes, you don't look at it as
sixty individual units. And in a pile of potatoes, one thing that's
problematic, it loses its identity. But if those objects are independently significant,
so one example is בעלי חיים, ba'alei chayim, but there's another example
of something that's what's called דבר שבמנין, davar shebimniyan, things that are
sold by number. So each one, each unit is important, okay, sixty,
well what would be an example? Because apples sometimes you sell by
weight, sometimes you sell by number. What are things that are only
sold by number? I guess you could say eggs, although eggs is
ironic. Do you sell bagels? Yeah, doesn't bagel? Yeah, although eggs is
ironic because eggs you sell by number but like one egg isn't
important. But maybe bagel, you know, you never buy one egg. But
maybe bagels, okay. So anyway, let's say you've got whatever, anyway in
that case, I don't know, but it's just funny, you know, because
anyway. You buy them by the dozen. Yeah, that's true. Anyway, things
that are independently significant, you don't look at it as though there's
like a big pile of it. You look at each one is
there, and if each one is there, then you don't have ביטול.
bittul. So a good example of that is live animals, okay. Every
live animal is significant, you don't look at it as just, you
know, as just a herd, although you could, we sometimes do, but
anyway, you look at it as sixty things. So therefore בעלי חיים
ba'alei chayim are not בטל, batel, okay. And therefore if one ox
gets שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, gets mixed up with nine innocent oxen,
if there's no ביטול bittul and the owner can't eat any of
them, the owners can't eat them, you can't say it's בטל. batel.
So they're all now אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Sorry, they're all אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, even if whatever we're going to do to them
because the laws of ביטול bittul don't apply. Oh, alright, if they're
already אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah says the חכמים, chachamim, let's just stone
them. So then at least we're stoning the right one, okay, so
that's what חכמים chachamim say, סוקלין אותן. soklin osan. רבי יהודה אומר
כונסן לכיפה, Rabbi Yehuda omer konesan lakippah, nah, stoning, I mean there's
a whole procedure for stoning, we learned it before. You're going to
do stoning on ten oxen because one of them is חייב? chayav?
Forget it, lock them all up, let them all die, nobody will
benefit from them, you know, maybe we, you know, will that be
יוצא yotzei the חיוב chiyuv of סקילה sekilah for that שור הנסקל,
shor haniskal, maybe, maybe not or whatever, but whatever, we're not going
to demand for בית דין beis din to stone all ten of
them, okay. So now you don't have the position before, which is,
it's ironic. Before when we said one ox got mixed up with
nine and they've all killed a person, we thought that the חכמים
chachamim say they all go scot-free. Now that we say one got
mixed up with nine and nine of them are innocent, we're reading
it that the חכמים, chachamim, everybody agrees you kill them. The question
is how do you kill them. The חכמים chachamim say you stone
them and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you lock them up, okay.
So that's now the explanation that we have settled with with the
משנה. Mishnah. I'm going to read that first line of רצח rotzeach
to not be about the ox, the first line is רצח rotzeach
is we don't know who the murderer was to begin with and
then everybody agrees that they go free and then you've got the
case of what do you call it, of a of a of
one שור הנסקל shor haniskal getting mixed up with nine innocent oxen
where there's no ביטול, bittul, they're all אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, so
everybody agrees they're going to get killed, they're going to die, the
חכמים chachamim say you stone them and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you lock them up, okay, so that's now the explanation that we
have settled with with the משנה. Mishnah. I'm going to read one
more line and then I will take the questions, okay. ותניא, v'tanya,
and now ותניא v'tanya sometimes is a question but sometimes is a
support. Here it's a support, okay, and we taught similarly in a
ברייתא, braisa, פרה שהמיתה, parah shehemitah, if you have a cow, not
an ox, okay, a female cow that killed, notice the feminine המיתה.
hemitah. ואחר כך ילדה, v'achar kach yaldah, and then it gave birth
after it became a פרה הנסקלת. parah haniskeles. ואחר כך ילדה, v'achar
kach yaldah, אם עד שלא נגמר דינה ילדה, im ad shelo nigmar
dinah yaldah, if it gave birth before גמר דין, gmar din, so
at the moment of גמר דין gmar din it was not carrying
its baby in its womb. So in that case the גמר דין
gmar din was only passed on the mother, not on the fetus,
okay. In that case ולד מותר, velad muttar, the child is not,
does not become a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, and the child could
be eaten because the דין din was passed after the mother had
given birth,
okay. אם משנגמר דינה ילדה, im mishenigmar dinah yaldah, but if however
it was pregnant when the גמר דין gmar din was passed, then
the גמר דין gmar din was passed on the mother with the
child. Now this presumably is even if it got pregnant after it
gored, you know, it's not like the child was part of its
body when it did the act of goring, that's not clear here
but it seems to be that that could be the case, okay.
It doesn't matter, it was part of the body when the דין
din was passed and therefore the דין din was passed, it's like
עובר ירך אמו, ubar yerech imo, we see the fetus as part
of the mother's body, and therefore when the דין din was passed
it was passed on this part of the mother's body. And now
that it gave birth after the גמר דין, gmar din, like let's
say the mother for example got fatter, okay, after you know, she
put on a hundred pounds after she became a, after she did
the goring, we wouldn't say that those hundred pounds, if you could
identify them, you know, those are מותר בהנאה. muttar behana'ah. Doesn't matter,
that's how big she was at the גמר דין, gmar din, her
whole body. Entire body at this moment becomes אסור בהנאה, asur behana'ah,
becomes a שור הנסקל. Shor Haniskal. So same too here, if she
got pregnant after she gored, that fetus is now part of her
body, it became... it becomes a שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal and if
she gives birth after the גמר דין, Gmar Din, it remains forbidden.
Okay, אם משנגמר דינה ועד שמילדה ולדה אסור. im mishenigmar dina ve-ad
she-meyaldah veladah asur. Okay,
so we're going to go back to explore that case of the
fetus, that was fascinating, but the reason initially we're quoting this ברייתא
Baraita is for the next line. Okay, נתערב באחרים ואחרים באחרים, nit'arev
ba-acherim ve-acherim ba-acherim,
forget the fetus. This שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal
or פרה הנסקלת Parah Ha-niskelet that got mixed up with... wouldn't it
be נתערבה nit'arva then? That's the ולד, vlad, no? Yeah, maybe you're
right, or maybe we're just using the generic, or maybe you're right,
maybe it's the ולד vlad in the case that was forbidden. Anyway,
a שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal gets mixed up with a herd of
other, of other similar animals. And not only that, this is even
a little bit crazy here why we go this far. Sometimes we
go this far by like עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but why we
go this far is not so clear. Okay, you've got you know,
the cows here, right?
You got these cows, okay,
and then whatever, and then you've got one cow that gets mixed
up but you can't identify it. We can identify it, but you
can't. Okay, so now this case they're all אסור, asur, right? Okay,
because you don't know which one is the פר הנסקל. Par Haniskal.
Now let's say here's this other herd. Okay, what happens is one
animal from here, one animal from here goes into that other herd.
Okay, so why don't we say okay, you don't even know that
the שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal got mixed up into herd number two,
right? So let's assume that at least here well most likely is
if there are ten animals, most likely it wasn't the שור הנסקל
Shor Haniskal that got here. So let's let the second herd be
okay. Nope! This herd is okay and the herd that that herd
got mixed up into is... I'm sorry, this herd is forbidden, and
even if one animal goes to the next herd the next herd
is also forbidden. So that seems quite extreme. Okay, we're not going
to worry about why that is, but that is what... but once
we're forbidding this we're forbidding even the second case. So if it
was your herd and you weren't careful and then you know it
got mixed into my herd can I get compensation for you? Ah,
that's like a case, that's a good question. That's a case of
like you know היזק שאינו ניכר, Hezek She-eino Nikar, and here it
wasn't בכוונה, be-kavanah, it was בשוגג, be-shogeg, so normally היזק שאינו ניכר
Hezek She-eino Nikar there isn't תשלומים tashlumin בשוגג. be-shogeg. So you might
have ruined my whole life. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, exactly. לעיין, Le-ayein, finishing
the sentence and then there are questions and I'm taking them all.
Okay. Anyway, נתערב באחרים ואחרים באחרים, nit'arev ba-acherim ve-acherim ba-acherim, so what
do you do? כונסן לכיפה, Kunsan le-kippah, so they all have to
die. How do they die? Because you can't get הנאה hana'ah from
any of them. So the first opinion is you put them all
in prison, okay, which parallels Rabbi Yehuda, כונסן לכיפה. Kunsan le-kippah. Rabbi
Eliezer ben Rabbi Shimon says מביאן לבית דין וסוקלן, mevian le-veit din
ve-sokelan, you stone them, which parallels the חכמים, Chachamim, or at least
the way we've re-read the חכמים—it Chachamim wasn't in our משנה, Mishnah,
but we've re-read the חכמים, Chachamim, which like we took this ברייתא
Baraita and pushed it into our משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so here you
have that debate of the שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal that gets mixed
up with innocent oxen. Do you lock them in prison or do
you stone it? And that's our claim of what's going on at
the end of the משנה. Mishnah. And the beginning of the משנה
Mishnah is that we don't know who the, what do you call...
you know, we don't know who the murderer was to begin with
and in that case everybody agrees that the murderer goes off scot-free
because what are we supposed to do? Okay, now I got to
a period. Question, Michael. And my question is this. So you know
according to our הוה אמינא hava amina that you know we thought
that it was an actual murderer and you know and then he
got mixed up with others, whatever was. So you know, I'm just
trying to think according to that then when while a case is
going on, yeah, am I just like free to come and go
as he will? He's not like kept in confinement or something like
that? You know, is he able to go home and... Oh yeah,
so that's a case about... so that's a good point, you know,
what do you do? Do we have a jail to hold the
person who... while he's under trial? So the גמרא Gemara before actually
learns from you know, from it says like כי לא פורש להם
ki lo parash lahem whatever, you know, ויניחהו במשמר, vayannichuhu bamishmar,
right,
to learn actually that חובשוהו. chovshuhu. But that was a case where...
it was a case where the חובשוהו chovshuhu was because it wasn't
clear yet whether the guy was going to live or die, if
I remember the case, right? The murder victim was going to live
or die, if I remember correctly. So that was a case where
you clearly held a person until you could determine. A case where
we haven't decided yet that the guy did the act, right, there
was not a good basis I think for saying that it was...
that you would hold the guy. Look, again I would assume that
it's a matter of practice they obviously did it if they thought
the guy was you know a flight risk, but like all of
that was just like communal institutions. It wasn't like based in Torah,
the same way כיפה kippa was a communal institution. Okay, but I
would have to go back to look at the case about חובשוהו,
chovshuhu, but if memory serves that was only when... actually it was
just like yesterday's דף, daf, wasn't it? About like
about...
yeah, it was
ע"ח ע"ב. ayin chet amud bet. כי לא פורש. Ki lo parash.
My bad. So that you
knew the guy did the act and you didn't know if the
victim was going to die. Okay, if you don't have yet, if
you're still holding the case and you haven't known that the guy's
done the act, there's no principle based on that. But I would
imagine as a matter of just, you know, a communal institution that
they would do that. Right. That's how we can see separately discussing
getting mixed up because, right, we didn't, it's not. Right. Right. Yes.
Okay, Charlie. Oh, אבא חלפתא Abba Halaphta was Rabbi Yossi's father. Ah,
of course, thank you. I missed that point. So it wasn't just
a random person who was chosen as a צדיק. tzaddik. Even my
father! Right, right. Hence the אבא, Abba, but okay, he was called
אבא חלפתא Abba Halaphta by others as well. Yes, thank you. Yes.
So, even if she was found liable for execution and she was
pregnant, would they wait to execute her until she gave birth to
the child? Oh, so I was going to mention that because we
also were just, because the whole issue about we discussed, we've been
discussing anyway the whole issue about, right, you know, abortion because it's
not a capital crime, we had it before in נתכוין להרוג את
זה והרג את זה, niskayven l'harog es zeh v'harag es zeh, somebody
tried to kill, or נפלה, nafleh, I forgot what it was anyway.
Somebody tried to, not נפלה, nafleh, עובר, ubar, somebody tried to kill
a fetus, kill the person, right, it's not a capital crime. So
how bad is it? How does the הלכה halacha treat abortion? Right,
that's a huge question. So there is exactly a discussion about a
pregnant woman and whether we wait for her to give birth or
we don't wait for her to give birth. And actually, there are
cases where we don't wait for her to give birth. Not only
do we not wait for her to give birth,
the גמרא Gemara bizarrely says that it would be actually seen as
more,
like, less disfiguring or less somehow offensive to her, it's hard to
understand what I'm about to say, but anyway, for what some type
of a reason, the גמרא Gemara says we actually would first abort
the fetus and then we would execute her. So we're actively aborting
the fetus. It's not just like we're executing her and... but there
was a גמר דין. gmar din. There was a גמר דין gmar
din on her. And we wouldn't necessarily wait until she... No, but
the problem about waiting till the גמר דין gmar din is that
it becomes a question of עינוי הדין inuy hadin or whatever, you
know, anyway, not, not here the case at all. Anyway, so anyway,
we're not dealing with that yet, but if there was a גמר
דין, gmar din, okay, you would not wait for her to give
birth and you would even actively abort the fetus first. So that
for some is a very strong evidence that there's, that there's, you
know, that that like, that you know, that there's no independent status
of the fetus, it's just seen as a part of the mother,
and therefore, you know, and it's all part of executing the mother
and so on. Others want to say it's different because the גמר
דין gmar din makes the fetus like have that status of deserving
to die and it allows us to abort, but like it wouldn't
generally be true. Okay, but that's, but there are just, there are
explicit discussions about that that factor into the הלכתי halachic debate about
the status of abortion. I think it's even coming up if I
remember. So we're actually going to get to it. Okay. All right.
Yes. Good. We've answered everybody's questions. Moving on. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So we've explained the משנה, Mishnah, but
now we've introduced this interesting case about the fetus and the פרה
הנסקלת, parah haniskeles, okay, where I said it's like presumably even if
it got pregnant later, if it was part of the mother when
the דין din was passed, then it was passed on the whole
fatter mother. Okay, so now we're going to explore this. Let's take
a look. אמר מר אם עד שלא נגמר דינה ילדה הולד מותר.
amar mar im ad shelo nigmar dina yaldah havlad mutar. Okay, if
it was a גמר דין, gmar din, if it gave birth before
גמר דין, gmar din, it's permissible. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואף
על גב דכי נגחה הויא מעוברת. v'af al gav d'chi nagcha hava
meuberes. Even if it was pregnant when it gored, right? So there
are three scenarios, let's draw the three scenarios. Okay.
Scenario number one, please excuse my stick drawings of my, here, okay,
that's goring, okay, here's the dead person, he's got arms, so that's
how you know he's a person. Okay, here's the dead person, I
have to actually draw them, leave it like here, whatever. Okay. So,
I guess he has to have four legs, okay, and here's the
dead person who he killed, make X's in the eyes, okay. So,
that's that, okay, then that's stage one, then stage two, it got
pregnant, okay, so here,
okay, and then stage three, okay, it was the גמר דין. gmar
din. Okay, so scenario number one is, okay, and here I guess
will be the בית דין beis din sitting, and giving it its
גמר דין. gmar din. שבעים וארבעה רבותיי shivim v'arba'ah rabosai here they're
sitting. Okay fine. Okay,
so that's the גמר דין. gmar din. Okay, so scenario number one,
the first scenario is it got pregnant in the middle, okay, and
then it had the גמר דין gmar din and it gave birth
after, okay, it was still pregnant at the time. Okay, the second
scenario is that it was the same, but it gave birth here,
okay, here there was a birth and then at the גמר דין
gmar din it was no longer pregnant. Okay, here's the little baby
calf. Okay, there's the little baby calf. Okay, I'll just do A,
B, C. Okay. So this is scenario number one, this is scenario
number two, scenario number three, I mean actually I think there are
four scenarios. Okay, is that it was pregnant when it gored. Okay,
and then it, and then it was pregnant, wait was pregnant when
it
gored. Hold up. Was pregnant when it gored. Yeah, was pregnant when
it gored. Then it gave birth. Okay, here's a little baby calf.
Okay, and here's the גמר דין. Gmar Din. All right. I don't
know if this is helpful, my little pictures. All right. So let's
talk about what happened. In this case, even though the fetus wasn't
part of the goring, it is part of its body at the
גמר דין. Gmar Din. Okay, so if it's part of its body
at the גמר דין, Gmar Din, that's obvious that the fetus is
אסור. assur. Okay, 'cause the גמר דין Gmar Din goes on that
little baby fetus. Okay, and that's clear that that's אסור. assur. Okay.
In this scenario, okay, it wasn't part of the goring, it wasn't
part of the גמר דין, Gmar Din, so that's going to be
מותר. muttar.
Everybody get that? Okay. In this case, now I'll just draw this
again just so people, okay.
Okay. Sorry. In this case, okay, it was part of the goring
and not part of the גמר דין. Gmar Din. So the פשט
pshat of our משנה mishna is, the פשט pshat of our ברייתא
baraita is that as long as the mother wasn't pregnant at the
גמר דין, Gmar Din, the baby gets off scot-free because it wasn't
judgment. So the question is, it sounds like even in this case
the baby gets off scot-free. But רבא Rava says that even if
it wasn't at the גמר דין, Gmar Din, since it was part
of the goring, then the baby also has to come to court
and we'll have a separate גמר דין Gmar Din on the baby.
Okay, because it was part of the act of the goring. Okay,
so that's our question. Our משנה mishna makes it sound like this
case it's מותר, muttar, a ברייתא baraita rather, because it sounds like
only in this case is it אסור. assur. I should do this
in
red. I'm sorry, so we're about to read it then. Okay, I'll
draw that in red. אסור. assur. But we're going to,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so let's read that
again. So the גמרא Gemara says,
it part here participated in the goring. Yeah, but it added weight
to the mother, whatever, so that added some force. It wasn't to
blame, okay, but it wasn't just a bystander. Okay, so it says
like this. It says, so let's take a look. אמר מר: Amar
Mar: אם עד שלא נגמר דינה ילדה, Im ad shelo nigmar dina
yalda, if it gave birth
before. Okay, ולדה מותר. vlada mutar. ואף על גב דשכיחא כהאי מעוברת,
Va'af al gav deshchina k'hai me'abra, even if it was pregnant at
the act of goring, as long as there was no גמר דין
Gmar Din on it, you're
okay. But the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, והאמר רבא: v'hamar Rava: ולדו נוגחת אסור.
vlado nogahat assur. היא וולדה נגחו. Hi u'vladah naghu. If a fetus
was in the mother when it gored, it's forbidden even if, we
understand רבא Rava to mean, it gave birth before גמר דין. Gmar
Din. You would bring it in for its own גמר דין Gmar
Din because it was part of the act. ולדו נרבעת אסור. Vlado
nirva'at assur. This is a harder issue, Dave, to understand. If the
mother was pregnant and a man did an act of bestiality on
the animal, then the fetus also had an act of bestiality done
on it. That's a bizarre idea because that obviously didn't add to
the act. Okay. היא וולדה נרבעו. Hi u'vladah nirvu. No, the act
was done to it as well. So according to רבא, Rava, you
do a separate גמר דין Gmar Din on the fetus. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says that's not this ברייתא. baraita. This ברייתא baraita
seems to contradict that. All right. So אימא סיפא. eima seifa. So
here's how we have to reread the ברייתא. baraita. אימא eima you
should say: אם עד שלא נגמר דינה עיברה וילדה ולדה מותר. Im
ad shelo nigmar dina ibra veyalda, vlada mutar. אם משנגמר דינה עיברה
וילדה ולדה אסור. Im mishe'nigmar dina ibra veyalda, vlada assur. So fine.
So our case is fine. So the ברייתא baraita is saying this
case is אסור, assur, before גמר דין Gmar Din it became pregnant.
So even if it wasn't part of the act, it was part
of the גמר דין. Gmar Din. Okay. And when is it מותר?
muttar? It's מותר muttar only in case number two, that before גמר
דין Gmar Din it both became pregnant and it gave birth. Okay.
So it wasn't part of the goring and it wasn't part of
the גמר דין. Gmar Din. Okay, so let's read that again. Okay.
And רבא's Rava's case of number three, we're going to say is
now going to be אסור. assur. Okay. So that's רבא's Rava's case
because it was part of the goring. So let's read that
again. אימא, eima, if before גמר דין Gmar Din it got pregnant,
like case number one it got pregnant after,
I'm sorry, I read that wrong. Case number three,
case number two. Okay. אימא: eima: אם עד שלא נגמר דינה עיברה
וילדה. Im ad shelo nigmar dina ibra veyalda. It got pregnant after...
the goring, and it gave birth after the goring, so both the
goring and the גמר דין gmar din it was not pregnant, then
ולד מותר, vlad muttar, then it’s okay. That’s case number two. אם
משנגמר דינה עיברה וילדה, im mishe-nigma dina ibra veyalda, if however it
got pregnant after the goring... עיברה, ibra,
excuse me, אם משנגמר דינה עיברה וילדה im mishe-nigma dina ibra veyalda
ולד אסור. vlad assur. If however it got pregnant after the goring
and it only gave birth after the גמר דין, gmar din, then
it’s forbidden. Okay, so we’re saying the ברייתא Braita is contrasting case
number one and case number two. Okay, when is it מותר? muttar?
When it became pregnant and gave birth after the goring. Okay, so
that’s when it was not part of the goring and it was
not part of the גמר דין. gmar din. When is it אסור?
assur? If it became pregnant after the goring and gave birth after
the גמר דין. gmar din. Then it was part of the גמר
דין. gmar din. רבא's Rava's case was not discussed by the ברייתא.
Braita. Case number three where it was pregnant at the goring and
then gave birth, that’s not being discussed. And that’s רבא's Rava's case.
Okay? So that’s how we’ve reconciled it. So now the גמרא Gemara
says one minute. הניחא למאן דאמר זה וזה גורם אסור. ha nicha
leman de-amar zeh ve-zeh gorem assur. So I get the גמרא Gemara
says in this case, case number two, right,
why is it, one minute, I think I jumped ahead.
Yes, I did jump ahead. Okay, I’m sorry, I apologize, I’m going
too far to the end.
Three is רבא. Rava. But there’s another scenario which
is,
what about if it was not pregnant here,
okay, not pregnant here, and then at stage number D it got
pregnant and gave birth after the גמר דין? gmar din? Everybody get
that case?
Probably not, but let’s just assume they did. Okay, so in this
case you say, well what’s the problem? It wasn’t part of the
goring, it wasn’t part of the גמר דין, gmar din, what’s the
problem? The problem is since it’s a שור הנסקל shor haniskal here,
or פרה הנסקלת, para haniskelet, and then it got pregnant and gave
birth, so that’s something that came from a forbidden thing. The cow
was forbidden, it got pregnant and gave birth. This is like it's
the same way the cow's milk is forbidden because even if the
milk was produced after it was a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, right?
So the baby was produced after it was a שור הנסקל, shor
haniskal, it was a product of a forbidden thing, that should be
forbidden. So for now we’re thinking that the case that we’re saying
אסור assur is actually that it only became pregnant after the גמר
דין. gmar din. So now the גמרא's Gemara's going to question that.
הניחא למאן דאמר זה וזה גורם אסור. ha nicha leman de-amar zeh
ve-zeh gorem assur. That’s fine if you say when there are two
causative things that bring something about it’s forbidden. If one of them
is forbidden and one is permissible, what’s the big... because it’s not
just the cow that produced the baby, right? Who else produced the
baby? Or at least contributed? The father. At least he had a
whole one minute of participation in the act.
Okay, right? The mother is pregnant for nine months, the father did
one minute of his
job. Anyway, so
actually the גמרא Gemara says, so that’s a question really if you
do look at the father, how much you look at him as
a זה וזה גורם. zeh ve-zeh gorem. But the father did contribute.
So therefore in your scenario where it became pregnant afterwards, the baby
is only forbidden if we think because it's not only the product
of a forbidden thing, it's a product of a forbidden thing and
a permissible thing. So that’s called זה וזה גורם. zeh ve-zeh gorem.
So if you say זה וזה גורם zeh ve-zeh gorem is forbidden,
then fine, the baby is forbidden. אלא למאן דאמר זה וזה גורם
מותר, ella leman de-amar zeh ve-zeh gorem muttar, but when it has
two things that brought it about it’s permissible because it wasn't only
created from a forbidden thing, מה איכא למימר? ma ika le-meimar? So
how would this case not be a problem because it also had
the father here? אלא אמר רבינא אימא, ella amar Ravina eima, so
this is what I was saying before, I was jumping to the
answer. אם עד שלא נגמר דינה עיברה וילדה ולד מותר. im ad
shelo nigma dina ibra veyalda vlad muttar.
Okay, so back to case number two. If it wasn't pregnant when
it got born, when it gored, got pregnant, gave birth, and wasn't
pregnant at the גמר דין, gmar din, so then it totally is
fine because it wasn't pregnant at either of the two critical junctures.
Okay? ואם עד שלא נגמר דינה
עיברה, ve-im ad shelo nigma dina ibra, but if your case number
one, wasn't pregnant at the goring, became pregnant in the middle, okay,
and it was pregnant at the time of the גמר דין, gmar
din, so the דין din was passed on the fetus, ומשנגמר דינה
ילדה, u-mishe-nigma dina yalda, and then it gave birth after the גמר
דין, gmar din, then it’s forbidden, ואסור, ve-assur, עובר ירך אמו. ubar
yerech imo. Okay, so we’re not going to deal with that other
case. That’s too complicated. This case, when... pregnant only at the גמר
דין Gmar Din is forbidden because it's a part of the mother
and the גמר דין Gmar Din was passed on the fetus as
well. This case, when it wasn't present at either endpoint, it's permissible.
Why should it be forbidden? And this is רבא's Rava חידוש, chidush,
when it was pregnant at the time of the goring but not
at the גמר דין, Gmar Din, because it was part of the
act of goring, then we're going to bring in the baby and
pass the גמר דין Gmar Din on the baby as well, even
if at the time of the גמר דין, Gmar Din, it's actually
it's no longer part of the mother. Okay. They stone the calf.
They stone the little baby calf. Okay, yes. The Artscroll is adding
a fence that I don't know where they're getting this idea that
they're saying רבא Rava said that the offspring of a pregnant goring
cow is forbidden for being offered as a sacrifice. Oh, thank you.
I didn't mention that. So yes, so the original context of רבא's
Rava statement, because the question is why does רבא Rava say אסור
assur or מותר? muttar? Why doesn't רבא Rava say סוקלין אותו, soklin
oso, whether you stone it? So the original context of רבא's Rava
statement, thank you for mentioning, is that there are not two witnesses
that saw the act. So if there's not two witnesses, we can't
stone it, but if the owners admit it or there's one witness,
at least because we know it did the goring, it can't be
used as a sacrifice. But the גמרא Gemara assumes, but not assumes,
like the general rule is you wouldn't say that unless it were
also true that if there were two witnesses you would stone it.
So although רבא Rava is discussing because he uses the word אסור
assur and מותר, muttar, which as opposed to סוקלין אותו soklin oso
or חייב chayav or פטור, patur, so it shows that we're talking
about a sacrifice, that's its original context, the same would be true
if there were two witnesses whether you would stone it or not
stone it. Thank you for that clarification. Okay, so now let's continue.
Okay, it says the following. כל חייבי מיתות. Kol chayvei misas. We
finally ברוך השם baruch Hashem get to the next part of the
משנה. Mishna. Okay, so the next part of the משנה Mishna is
that, you know, one type of a person with one type of
a conviction gets mixed up with other people of a conviction, of
a different conviction, different types of a death penalty and therefore you
can only give them the lighter death penalty, so everybody gets the
lighter and that led to a whole debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and the חכמים Chachamim which one was the lighter, the whole
things that we came out and which was the heavier, things we
dealt with before. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
the גמרא Gemara has a different issue though. Why is it so
obvious you can give everybody the lighter one? Okay, שמע מינה shema
mina should we infer from this that מוסרא, musra, not מותרא, mutra,
מותרה, mutara, מוסרא musra were warned like התראה. hatra’ah. Somebody that is
warned לדבר חמור, ledavar chamur, הוי מוסרא לדבר קל havei musra ledavar
kal should be seen as warned for something weighty and warned for
something light? Because the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the warning is
not just don't do that act, if you do that act you
will transgress the פסוק pasuk of you know לא תרצח lo sirtzach
and you'll be חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Okay, that's not enough. What
you have to also say is you'll transgress the פסוק pasuk of
לא תרצח, lo sirtzach, you'll be חייב מיתה, chayav misa, and the
מיתה misa is, you know, סייף. sayif. Okay, so these עדים edim
have to be like real תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Wait, wait, wait,
let me check. Let me get out the רמב"ם. Rambam. Let me
check. Okay, the מיתה's misa gotta be... Okay, so anyway, so it
assumes you need the warning about what death penalty you're going to
get. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but this guy only accepted
the death penalty it was explicitly said that he was going to
get, you know,
סייף. sayif. He did not accept the death penalty of שריפה. sereifa.
So even if we say that שריפה sereifa is lighter, right, so
I mean or whatever, חנק, chenek, whatever it is. He didn't accept
the death penalty of חנק. chenek. So even if we say that
חנק chenek is lighter, but that wasn't the death penalty that gives
us all that he explicitly accepted upon himself. Again, this works with
the idea that בית דין Beis Din only has a license to
do what it's doing because he explicitly accepted it upon himself. So
should we infer from this that if somebody accepts התראה hatra'ah for
a weighty death penalty, it implicitly gives us license to do a
lighter death penalty as well? Because that seems to be the case
in the משנה. Mishna. שמע מינה shema mina should we infer from
this that מוסרא לדבר חמור, musra ledavar chamur, somebody who is warned
for a weighty death penalty, הוי מוסרא לדבר קל havei musra ledavar
kal is considered to be warned for a lighter one? So the
משנה Mishna says no. אמר רבי ירמיה הכא במאי עסקינן כשהתרו בו
סתם. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah hacha mai askinan keshehisru bo stam. You know
what? They didn't tell him which death penalty. They just said if
you do it you're חייב מיתה chayav misa and you don't need
to say exactly which death penalty. So since he generically accepted upon
himself a death penalty, then we can give him whichever one. But
if he only accepted it's possible to say, we're leaving it as
an open question, but it's possible to say that if he only
accepted upon himself a specific death penalty, we would not have a
license to do another one, even a lighter death penalty. Okay now,
who is it? Is it okay to just give somebody a generic
התראה hatra'ah about death penalty without being specific? Yes, according to one
ברייתא Braisa there is. One תנא Tanna there is. והאי תנא הוא,
Vehai Tanna hu, it's the following תנא, Tanna, דתנו רבנן בברייתא ובשאר
חייבי מיתות שבתורה. detanu rabanan bebaraisa uveshar chayvei misas shebatorah. So it's
in the context of you don't give warning to a מסית, meisis,
to a seducer. Okay, but all the other, I mean a seducer...
to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But all other death penalties, אין מיתים
אותם, ein meisim osom, you would not execute them, אלא בעדה, ela
b'edah, you would need a עדה, edah, you would need a בית
דין beis din of twenty-three. You need okay the עדים edim and
witnesses, you need those two for a what do you call it?
for a seducer as well. But the התראה, hatra'ah, meaning a seducer
you don't need to warn, seducer to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But
all other people you have to warn them, and it what does
that warning consist of? עד שיודיעו שהוא חייב מיתת בית דין, ad
sheyodi'u shehu chayav misas beis din, until you have to tell him
that he's deserving of the death penalty. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda
omer, עד שיודיעו באיזו מיתה הוא נהרג. ad sheyodi'u b'eizo misa hu
neherag. No, you have to be more specific, you have to say
which death penalty. Okay? So what's that debate about? תנא קמא
ילף ממקושש, Tanna Kamma yalif mi'mekoshesh, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma learns
from the מקושש, mekoshesh, the wood-gatherer who broke שבת, shabbos, right? They
didn't know they knew he would get the death penalty, מחלליה מות
יומת, mechallelo mos yumas, right? But they didn't know which death penalty.
God had to tell them: you stone him. Okay? So the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says, "Ah! So you see there!" They could have
only given him a generic warning and therefore and that was enough.
You didn't need a specific warning of which death penalty. רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, Rebbi יהודה Yehuda would say back: מקושש הוראת שעה. mekoshesh
hora'as sha'ah. So that was a special, you know, one-time ruling. Okay?
Because they had to put him to death and the death penalty
hadn't been explicated yet. Okay? But once the death penalty was explicated,
you have to give the person the specific one. So now, within
רבי יהודה'ס Rebbi Yehuda's position that you have to give a specific
death penalty, it might very well be that, you know, if you
accept that one, you're not allowed to give a lighter death a
lighter punishment, even a lighter one. Alright? Which, by the way, is
interesting because you might remember before the גמרא Gemara had a discussion
about, like, מות יומת הרוצח mos yumas harotzeach teaches you that if
you can't kill him with the official death penalty, you kill him
in any way you can. Like, let's say the רוצח rotzeach was
running away and the only way you can get to him after
גמר דין gmar din is by, you know, by shooting him. So
you could shoot him. Alright? So, how does that fit into this?
Because here, you know, here's a case where you can you won't
be able to do the normal one, the one he should get
because you don't know who's who. Is it only a דין din
by רוצח rotzeach that you're allowed to stop him in any way
you can? Anyway, that's left open. But the גמרא Gemara understands that
it's possible for רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda we maybe yes, maybe no,
but it's certainly possible that we would say that if
you you A, you have to accept for רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
the specific death penalty. And if you did, then we might not
have license to give you the lighter one. But for the חכמים,
Chachamim, now, it sounds like for the חכמים, Chachamim, if you accepted
the generic death penalty, then of course we have license to give
you a lesser one. But the גמרא Gemara implies that for the
חכמים, Chachamim, although you didn't have to you didn't have to explicate
which death penalty, if you did explicate which death penalty, then you
also might be limited and not have a license to do the
other one. Okay? So this is very interesting because this גמרא Gemara
imagines cases where you do not have a license to give even
a lesser death penalty. And before we said that actually if you
can't kill the guy with the official one, you can kill him
with another one. So how to make those two work is not
so clear. Okay? So yes, in greater extension of the intentions that
we've been discussing through all these different cases. Oh,
you mean because
right, so it's not the intention of the crime, but the intention
almost of the punishment of the crime has to be right. You're
right, I mean, it really shows how much we how much we
do it. So take take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, the issue
I was raising, four lines from the bottom. תוספות Tosafos says, the
very bottom of the דף: daf: ואם תאמר, v'im tomar, תוספות Tosafos
says, if you say: וכי לא הוי נמי התראה לדבר קל? v'chi
lo havei nami hatra'ah l'davar kal? Fine. Let's say the התראה hatra'ah
did not work for something lighter. Okay? ותיפוק ליה דהכא חייב דממה
נפשך נהרג, v'sifok leh d'hacha chayav d'mimah nafshach neherag, שהרי אם אתה
יכול להמיתו במיתה הכתובה בו אתה ממיתו בכל מיתה שאתה יכול, sheharei
im atah yachol l'hamiso b'misa haksiva bo atah memiso b'chol misa she'atah
yachol, that you can kill him out anyway you want, ושם פירשתי.
v'sham peirashti. So go look what I wrote over there. Because that
wasn't so helpful. Okay? I actually forgot what תוספות Tosafos wrote there.
Let me see if I can pick out the key line here
very quickly. Yeah,
so תוספות Tosafos says that it could be it's only a license
for very specific cases like a murderer, or it's only a license
if the guy is like running away. But in this case where
nobody is running away, you know, maybe we all lock him up
in prison, we have other alternatives. Okay? So that's a special license
maybe in only very specific cases like a murderer or that he's
escaping. But if he's not escaping or not a murderer, and then
if maybe we won't be able to kill him because we don't
know which execution to give and maybe we'll just lock him up.
Alright? So that's what תוספות Tosafos says. Alright? So that's very interesting.
Do you need a specific התראה hatra'ah what type of death penalty?
And if you do have a specific one, do you have a
license to do a lighter one? Last point of the
משנה. mishnah. הנסקלין בנשרפין. haniskalin b'nisrafin. So it people that get סקילה
skila gets mixed up with people that get שריפה. sreifa. So and
then רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says, so רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon thinks
that שריפה sreifa is weightier. So he says you give them all
סקילה, skila, okay? Because he thinks שריפה sreifa is weightier. So מתקיף
לה רבי חזקיה לרמי. maskif lah Rebbi Chizkiya l'Rami. rates, רבי חזקיה
Rabbi Hizkiya when he was teaching this משנה mishnah taught it to
his son רמי Rami and he says הנשרפין בנסקלין. hanisrafin baniskalin. Those
that get שריפה sreifa got mixed up with those that get סקילה,
skila, which means that you assume that the second one, the crowd
that got mixed up into, is the bigger number. Okay, so an
individual, yeah, we'll erase our oxen and we'll replace it with people.
I'm better at drawing people, not really, but stick figures are easier
than stick figures of animals. Okay, so here are, here's a group
of people that are supposed to get סקילה, skila, okay, we'll signify
that by having stones raining down on them. Okay, and then one
guy who's supposed to get שריפה, sreifa, okay, okay, gets mixed up.
So that's
הנשרפין בנסקלין, hanisrafin baniskalin, okay? And then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon thinks
סקילה skila is lighter, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says so give
them all סקילה skila because סקילה skila is lighter. Okay, so that
was how he taught the
משנה. mishnah. מתני לה רבי חזקיה
לרמי בריה. Matni lah Rabbi Hizkiya l'Rami breih. הנשרפין בנסקלין. hanisrafin baniskalin.
Somebody with שריפה sreifa gets mixed up with people that are חייב
סקילה. chayav skila.
רבי שמעון אומר ידונו בסקילה שהשריפה חמורה, Rabbi Shimon omer yidunu beskila
she'hasreifa chamura, they all get סקילה, skila, שהשריפה חמורה she'hasreifa chamura because
שריפה's sreifa weightier. Okay, fine. So אמר ליה רב יהודה, amar leh
Rav Yehuda, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who was also there in
the room because רמי Rami and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda were both
sons of רב חזקיה. Rav Hizkiya. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said,
אבא, Abba, לא תשני הכי, lo tishnei hachi, Dad, that's not how
you should teach the משנה. mishnah. Okay, מאי איריא דשריפה חמורה? mai
irya d'sreifa chamura? In this case the reason to say they all
get סקילה skila you don't have to say because סקילה skila is
a lighter punishment. Maybe the reason they all get סקילה skila is
because the majority get סקילה, skila, so maybe you just apply the
principle of majority rule. If the majority of the group gets סקילה,
skila, we'll just give סקילה skila to the whole group. So if
you want, your חידוש chiddush is that the only reason you get
סקילה skila is because סקילה's skila lighter, so tell it, give a
better scenario. This scenario might be because סקילה's skila the majority.
מאי איריא דשריפה חמורה? mai irya d'sreifa chamura? The reason you get
סקילה skila there wouldn't have to be because שריפה's sreifa weightier. תיפוק
ליה דרובא נסקלין נינהו. teipuk lei d'rubba niskalin ninhu. It could just
be because the majority gets סקילה. skila. So he said that back,
so רבי חזקיה Rabbi Hizkiya said back, אלא היכי אתני? ella heichi
asni? How do you think I should teach it? הנסקלין בנשרפין. haniskalin
banisrafin. So fine, let's say I said it was the reverse. Okay,
a guy that is supposed to be getting סקילה skila gets mixed
up with this group that's getting שריפה. sreifa. Okay, and then רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says even though there's only one guy getting סקילה,
skila, they all get סקילה skila because סקילה skila is lighter, okay?
That's a bigger חידוש. chiddush. Only one guy deserves סקילה skila but
since סקילה's skila lighter, they all get סקילה. skila. That's what you
want me to say?
אלא היכי אתני הנסקלין בנשרפין רבי שמעון אומר ידונו בסקילה שהשריפה חמורה.
ella heichi asni haniskalin banisrafin Rabbi Shimon omer yidunu beskila she'hasreifa chamura.
That works for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but then you get to
part two of the משנה. mishnah. אי הכי אימא סיפא? i hachi
ema seifa? But then look how the חכמים Chakhamim respond. וחכמים אומרים
v'Chakhamim omrim no, ידונו בשריפה שסקילה חמורה. yidunu besreifa she'skila chamura. No,
in that case they all get שריפה sreifa because סקילה's skila weightier,
שריפה's sreifa lighter. So he says fine, so that works for רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's a חידוש, chiddush, but when the חכמים Chakhamim
come back and say no, no, no, שריפה's sreifa lighter, they all
get שריפה, sreifa, but maybe they're all getting שריפה sreifa for the
חכמים Chakhamim because שריפה's sreifa the majority. תיפוק ליה דרובא נשרפין נינהו.
teipuk lei d'rubba nisrafin ninhu.
So one way or another way, for either רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
or the חכמים, Chakhamim, you know, it's not going to be such
a big חידוש chiddush because one of the crowds is going to
be the majority. גמרא gemara says no, התם רבנן הוא דקאמרי ליה
לרבי שמעון. hatam Rabbanan hu d'ka'amrei lei l'Rabbi Shimon.
No,
no, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is the one who taught the initial
thing, the חכמים Chakhamim are the respondents. So you want רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon to be saying the חידוש. chiddush. In this version, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying even though one guy gets סקילה, skila,
only one guy deserves סקילה, skila, I'm going to give them all
סקילה skila because סקילה skila is lighter. So he's saying the base
teaching and he's going to say it in a חידוש chiddush way.
The חידוש chiddush way is only one guy deserves it and they're
all going to get it. חכמים Chakhamim are only responding to the
scenario he laid out.
התם רבנן הוא דקאמרי ליה לרבי שמעון לדידך דאמרת שריפה חמורה? hatam
Rabbanan hu d'ka'amrei lei l'Rabbi Shimon l'dideich d'amart sreifa chamura? No, סקילה
חמורה. skila chamura. First of all, you should know רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, we disagree with your premise. שריפה sreifa is not weightier, the
weightier one is סקילה. skila. And if it was the reverse case,
whatever, you'd always give them שריפה sreifa even if שריפה sreifa was
a minority. So we disagree with your whole premise. But as far
as this case, this case anyway they, you know, you could argue
they get שריפה sreifa because שריפה's sreifa the majority. But whichever way
it is, we just disagree with your premise, which is basically the
גמרא gemara saying is you want the first opinion, the one who's
laying down the case, to be saying it in the way that's
a חידוש. chiddush. The חכמים Chakhamim then have to respond to the
case that was laid out. So since רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon lays
down the case and he says סקילה, skila, you want it to
be חידוש chiddush even though only one guy deserves סקילה, skila, they're
all going to get סקילה. skila. Okay? Good? Fine. So that's the
end of just explaining the משנה. mishnah. We're really not disagreeing, we're
just framing it in the most חידוש chiddush way. Now the גמרא
gemara at the end of this turns to a little discussion about
parental respect.
Okay, one wonders if you've got The whole little discussion of בן
סורר ומורה Ben Sorer Umoreh from the previous פרק perek in the
background. All right. You know, a lot of these cases of חיוב
מיתה, chiyuv misa, right, there's hitting your father and mother and wounding
them, there's cursing your father and mother. Anyway, I don't think so,
I think the גמרא gemara just needed to say it, but it's
worth remembering that there is a context here of חיוב מיתה chiyuv
misa by particular acts of parental disrespect. Anyway, so the גמרא gemara
says like this, or parental attack or offense. Anyway, אמר ליה רב
שמואל
לרב יהודה, Amar lei Rav Shmuel le-Rav Yehuda, so שמואל Shmuel said
to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שיננא, shinena, לא תימא ליה לאבוך הכי.
lo seima lei la-avuch hachi. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was like
שמואל's Shmuel major תלמיד talmid and often רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
things in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. And שמואל Shmuel often refers
to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda as שיננא, shinena, sharp one. Sometimes it's
seen as a compliment, sometimes it's seen as a little, a little
maybe jab. Okay, but whatever it is, he says, he heard about
this and שמואל Shmuel said, how can you talk to your father
like that? Dad, that's not the right way to teach it. That's,
you know, where's a little respect? Okay, דתניא, detanya, we taught a
ברייתא, braisa, הרי שהיה אביו עובר על דברי תורה, harei she-haya aviv
over al divrei Torah, let's say a father was actually transgressing and
you had to stop him from doing an עבירה, aveira, right? So
on the one hand, you're telling him something harsher that he's doing
an עבירה, aveira, but on the other hand, there's more of an
imperative to intervene. Okay, לא יאמר לו אבא עברת על דברי תורה.
lo yomar lo abba avarta al divrei Torah. Actually, that's less of
a חידוש chidush because that's about the past. Dad, you just did
a transgression. Right? Maybe if it's to stop him, you do have
more license. "Dad! Don't do that! That's חילול שבת!" chilul Shabbos! Okay,
because then you haven't said he's done something wrong yet, and maybe
actually there is more license. But if he actually, you certainly can't
say, "You know, what you just did was חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos,
I better not see you doing that again." Okay, you can't say
that to your father. Okay, אלא אומר לו אבא כך כתוב בתורה.
ela omer lo abba kach kasuv ba-Torah. You should say, "No, here's
what it says in the Torah." Now the גמרא, gemara, רש"י Rashi
says, the גמרא gemara says such things that you mean it like
rhetorically. "Really, Dad? Does it say you're allowed to do that in
the Torah? Turn on a light on שבת? Shabbos? I don't think
so." Okay, so obviously that would be disrespectful as well. So the
גמרא gemara says, סוף סוף היינו הך, sof sof hainu hach, if
you say it like that, it's also being, it's being explicitly critical
of your father. No, אלא אומר לו אבא מקרא כתוב בתורה כך.
ela omer lo abba mikra kasuv ba-Torah kach. Say, "Dad, but you
know, there's a פסוק pasuk in the Torah that says like לא
תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם." lo sevaru esh be-chol moshvoseichem. You know, so
you sort of, you don't directly say it as a criticism. You
sort of, sort of say like, "You know, like, oh, but you
know, like, that's so interesting because I thought that normally shouldn't that
be אסור, assur, you know, I thought that there's a פסוק pasuk
here that's relevant to this issue." So anyway, you do it in
obviously a way that is not seen, gets your message across, but
is not seen as criticizing. Okay, and therefore he says that you
don't say to your dad, "Dad, that's the wrong way to teach
the משנה." mishna. You should say like, "Wait a minute, wouldn't it
be a bigger חידוש chidush to teach it this way?" You know,
so there's ways you could say it without saying without being critical.
Okay, so that's the way that the גמרא gemara ends here. Okay,
it does raise an interesting question, what I said, which is maybe
if you have to intervene before it's done, like with an עבירה,
aveira, maybe you're given obviously more license. But anyway, okay, so we'll
pick up with the משנה mishna on
over יום טוב. Yom Tov. I'll send out the times. Okay, yes,
Charlie.
So one thing—